Guide to the Theodore Sizer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Theodore Sizer papers
1679-1992
MS 453
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.25
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, drawings for posters, bookplates, Christmas cards, and armorial designs for Yale College. Also included is material related to Theodore Sizer's service as an officer in the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section of the U.S. Army Air Corps during World War II. Important correspondents are Eric Gill, James Lukens McConaughy, Gifford Pinchot, Neal Lawson Lewis and Sir Edmund Kerchever Chambers. Also in the papers are grade and attendance books from his courses at Yale (1927-1955). Papers relating to the Yale University Art Gallery include correspondence and drafts for a "History of the Visual Arts at Yale, 1701-1957," material on James Jackson Jarves, and correspondence and notes on John Marshall Phillips who succeeded Sizer as director of the Art Gallery.
Sizer, Theodore, 1892-1967
Conditions Governing Access
Gradebooks are restricted until 2030.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 93-M-28 was the gift of Judith Ryland Sizer, 1992; Accession 99-M-86 was transfer from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1999; accession 2000-M-071 was the gift of Theodore R. Sizer, 1999; accession 2000-M-073 was transfer from Arts of the Book Collection, 1999.
Arrangement
Arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Theodore Sizer was born on March 19, 1892 in New York City. He received a B.S. degree from Harvard in 1915. He worked in the import-export business from 1915 until 1922 and served as a first lieutenant in the Army in World War I. He was curator at the Cleveland Museum of Art from 1922 to 1927, and a lecturer at Case Western Reserve College from 1924 to 1927. He became an associate professor of the history of art at Yale and associate director of the Yale Art Gallery in 1927. Sizer was a professor of art history at Yale University from 1931 until his retirement in 1957. He was director of the Yale University Art Gallery from 1940 to 1947. An expert on heraldry, he became the first Pursuivant of Arms at Yale University in 1963 and created banners for Yale and the city of St. Louis. Sizer died on June 21, 1967 in West Haven, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, drawings for posters, bookplates, Christmas cards, and armorial designs for Yale College. Also included is material related to Theodore Sizer's service as an officer in the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section of the U.S. Army Air Corps during World War II. Important correspondents are Eric Gill, James Lukens McConaughy, Gifford Pinchot, Neal Lawson Lewis and Sir Edmund Kerchever Chambers. Also in the papers are grade and attendance books from his courses at Yale (1927-1955). Papers relating to the Yale University Art Gallery include correspondence and drafts for a "History of the Visual Arts at Yale, 1701-1957," material on James Jackson Jarves, and correspondence and notes on John Marshall Phillips who succeeded Sizer as director of the Art Gallery.
Art; Heraldry; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; Art historians; Chambers, E. K. (Edmund Kerchever), 1866-1954; Gill, Eric, 1882-1940; Jarves, James Jackson, 1818-1888; Lewis, Neal Lawson; McConaughy, James L. (James Lukens), 1887-1948; Phillips, John Marshall, 1905-1953; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Sizer, Theodore, 1892-1967; Weir, Irene, 1863-1944; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Art Gallery; Yale University. Art Gallery. Jarves Collection
- Inventory, 1916-1966; 4.75 linear feet (13 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Early and Art Gallery correspondence (alphabetical), Circa 1928-(1940-1942)-1956
    - A - D (Box 1)
    - E - K (Box 2)
    - L - P, W, miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (chronological), [1925?]-1963 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and drawings re: Yale armorial banners designed by Sizer, 1956-1959 (Box 5)
  - Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section of the Military Government
    - Correspondence, 1943-1948 (Box 5)
    - Printed matter: articles and newspaper clippings, Circa 1945-1950 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbooks with mounted clippings, other printed matter, and some correspondence, 1942-1950 (Box 6)
    - Scrapbooks with mounted clippings, other printed matter, and some correspondence, 1942-1950 (Box 7)
  - Writings
    - "A Confidential and Informal Report regarding proposed Exhibitions of Australian and New Zealand Art...," Carnegie Corporation of New York: typescript, bound, with photographs, 1941 (Box 7)
    - John Marshall Phillips, 1905-1953: correspondence, notes, drafts, proofs, printed matter, photographs, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - Address at Seniors-Fellows Dinner, Davenport College, on Daniel Merriman's tenth anniversary as Master: carbon of typescript, 1956 May 9 (Box 7)
    - "Benjamin Silliman and His Uncle-in-Law Colonel Trumbull," paper read before the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences: carbon of typescript, with annotations, 1959 May 19 (Box 7)
    - "An Adventure: The Story of the Edwards Portraits": correspondence, annotated typescript, proofs, clippings, photographs, 1959 (Box 7)
    - "The Recollections of John Ferguson Weir": correspondence, typescript, notes, note cards, photographs, 1956-1958 (Box 8)
    - History of the Visual Arts at Yale, 1701-1957
      - Drafts, 1957 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, notes, note cards, printed matter, photographs, including early research on James Jackson Jarves, 1933-(1954-1957) (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, notes, note cards, printed matter, photographs, including early research on James Jackson Jarves, 1933-(1954-1957) (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, notes, note cards, printed matter, photographs, including early research on James Jackson Jarves, 1933-(1954-1957) (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, notes, note cards, printed matter, photographs, including early research on James Jackson Jarves, 1933-(1954-1957) (Box 11A)
      - "List of principal collections, bequests, gifts and funds of Yale University Art Gallery": typescript, note cards, undated (Box 12)
  - Writings of others
    - Song, "Lilli Marlene": manuscript, transcribed by John Marshall Phillips, copy of printed version, 1944 (Box 12)
    - Alfred Whitney Griswold, "Lines Composed in Honor of T. Sizer": carbon of typescript Robert Nanteuil's "Maxims," tr. H.-M. Cadgène, 1956 May 17, 1941 (Box 12)
  - Harvard University: The Signet Society Medal for Achievement in the Arts: certificate, 1966 April 30 (Box 12)
  - Grade and attendance books [restricted for 75 years], 1927-1955 (Box 13)
    Conditions Governing Access
    These records are restricted until 2030.
  - Oversize
    - Photograph of painting by John F. Weir of Robert W. Weir's studio, undated (Box 14)
    - Drawings for greeting cards, and printed copies, 1916-1961 (Box 14)
    - Armorial and bookplate drawings, 1959-1960, undated (Box 14)
    - Drawings for posters, 1960, 1962 (Box 14)
    - Certificates from Harvard University, Rowfant Club, American Antiquarian Society, New York Historical Society, and Massachusetts Historical Society, 1916-1954 (Box 14)
    - Design for arms (Morse and Stiles), undated (Box 14)
      General note
      Note: See also the John Trumbull Papers, MS 506, for Sizer materials concerning Trumbull's Auto-biography.
- Additional Material, 1992; Accession 1993-M-028; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1993 Feb
  Received from: Judith Ryland Sizer, 1992 Oct 15
  - THEODORE SIZER: A Centennial Album of His Life and Art, prepared by descendants of Theodore Sizer, 1992 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-086
  This addition contains material pertaining to the creation of the official flag of St. Louis, Missouri, designed by Theodore Sizer in conjunction with the bicentennial celebration in 1964.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research materials, sketches (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper/magazine clippings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-071
  - "A display of heraldry: manifesting a more easy access to the knowledge thereof than hath been hitherto published by any, through the benefit of method/whereunto it is now reduced by the study and industry of John Guillim, late pursuivant at arms," by John Guillim, fifth edition, 1679 [includes typed poem by A. Whitney Griswold for the presentation of volume to Sizer on the occasion of his retirement in 1956] (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-073
  - Correspondence [includes unidentified sketches], 1963, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arms, heraldic
    - Graduate School, 1965, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Morse College, 1959, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Banner [Yale College], 1959-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)